<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!---------------------------------------------------------------------------
-- 
-A  classes.xml                
--
-A  This file is part of ZigZag <http://schmidt.nuigalway.ie/zigzag>.
--
-Y  Copyright (C) 2010, Götz Pfeiffer 
--
-->

<!DOCTYPE Chapter SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd">

<Chapter Label="ch:classes">
<Heading>Conjugacy Classes.</Heading>

<#Include Label="Intro:Classes">

The functions described here are in the file <F>classes.g</F>.

<Section>
<Heading>Cyclic Shift Class Constructors and Methods.</Heading>

In this section I describe the functions that construct cyclic shift classes
and work on cyclic shift classes.

<#Include Label="CyclicShifts">

<#Include Label="IsCyclicShifts">

</Section>

<Section Label="Sect:CyclicShiftsAsSets">
<Heading>Set Methods for Cylic Shift Classes.</Heading>

Cyclic shift classes are domains and therefore all set theoretic functions described
in  chapter "Domains"  are also  applicable to  shapes.   This section
describes  which  functions  are  implemented  specially  for  cyclic shift classes.
Functions  not  mentioned here  are  handled  by  the default  methods
described in the respective sections of chapter "Domains".

More precisely, every cyclic shif class has as its operations record
<C>CyclicShiftsOps</C> which inherits from <C>DomainOps</C>
and overrides the methods below to make it work or to provide 
more efficient implementations.

<#Include Label="Elements(shifts)">

<#Include Label="Representative(shifts)">

</Section>

<Section Label="Sect:CycscRecords">
<Heading>Cyclic Shift Class Records.</Heading> 

Like all other domains cyclic shift classes are represented by
records.  While it is possible to construct such a record by hand it
is preferable to use the constructor function
<Ref Func="CyclicShifts"/>).<P/>

After such a record is created you can add more components.  But you
should not alter the values of components which are already
present.<P/>

A cyclic shift class record has the following <E>category components</E>.
<List>
<Mark>
  <C>isDomain</C>:
</Mark>
<Item>
  is always <K>true</K> since a cyclic shift class is a domain.
</Item>
<Mark>
  <C>isCyclicShifts</C>:
</Mark>
<Item>
  is always <K>true</K>.
</Item>
</List>
        
The following components are the <E>identification</E> components of a
cyclic shift class record.
<List>
<Mark>
  <C>W</C>:
</Mark>
<Item>
  is the Coxeter group this cyclic shift class refers to.
</Item>
<Mark>
  <C>w</C>:
</Mark>
<Item>
  is the element of <M>W</M> that generates this cyclic shift class.
</Item>
</List>
        
Other components which contain information about the cyclic shift
class may be added automatically over time.  These components are
better accessed through the functions that will create them if not
present.
<List>
<Mark><C>size</C>:</Mark>
<Item> is the  size of the cyclic shift class  and can be obtained  through the method
<C>Size</C>.
</Item>
<Mark><C>elements</C>:</Mark>
<Item> is the set of elements of  the cyclic shift class and can be obtained from the
        method <Ref Meth="Elements" Label="for cyclic shift classes"/>.
</Item>
<Mark><C>edges</C>:</Mark>
<Item> is the  set of edges  of the shape  and can be obtained through the
        method <Ref Meth="Edges" Label="for shapes"/>.
</Item>
<Mark><C>transversal</C>:</Mark>
<Item> is  the transversal of  the shape  and can  be obtained  through the
        method <Ref Meth="Transversal" Label="for shapes"/>.
</Item>
</List>

<#Include Label="Edges(shape)">

<#Include Label="Transversal(shape)">

</Section>

<Section Label="Sect:FurtherCyclicShifts">
<Heading>Further Methods for Conjugacy Classes.</Heading>

In this section I describe some methods for conjugacy classes, 
which are based on cyclic shift classes.

<#Include Label="CentralizerComplement">

</Section>

</Chapter>
